<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> – Concepts</title>
    <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Concepts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Architecture</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/architecture/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS is a software-defined storage platform for running stateful
applications in containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read about &lt;a href=&#34;https://storageos.com/storageos-cloud-native-storage&#34;&gt;the cloud native storage principles behind
StorageOS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, StorageOS aggregates storage attached to nodes in a cluster,
creates a virtual pool across nodes, and presents virtual volumes from the pool
into containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is agnostic to the underlying storage and runs equally on
bare metal, in virtual machines or on cloud providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/images/docs/concepts/storageos-cluster.png&#34; alt=&#34;StorageOS architecture&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS is deployed as one container on each node that presents or consumes
storage, available as &lt;code&gt;storageos/node&lt;/code&gt; on the Docker Hub. In Kubernetes,
this is typically managed as a daemonset, next
to the applications. StorageOS runs entirely in user space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS is designed to feel familiar to Kubernetes and Docker users. Storage
is managed through standard StorageClasses and PersistentVolumeClaims, and
features are controlled by Kubernetes-style labels and selectors, prefixed with
&lt;code&gt;storageos.com/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS uses the storage capacity from the nodes where it is installed to
provide thinly-provisioned volumes. That space is selected from the mount point
of &lt;code&gt;/var/lib/storageos/data&lt;/code&gt; on the host. It is recommended that disk devices
are used exclusively for StorageOS, as described in &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/managing-host-storage/&#34;&gt;Managing Host Storage
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any container may mount a StorageOS virtual volume from any node, regardless of
whether the container and volume are colocated on the same node or the volume is
remote. Therefore, applications may be started or restarted on any node and
access volumes transparently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volumes are provisioned from a storage pool and are thinly provisioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, volumes are cached to improve read performance and compressed to
reduce network traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Available memory&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;% of overall memory reserved by StorageOS for caching&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;3 GB or less&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;3-8 GB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;5%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;8-12 GB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;12 GB or more&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Clusters</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/clusters/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/clusters/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS clusters represent groups of nodes which run a common distributed
control plane, and aggregate their storage into one or more
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/pools&#34;&gt;pools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, a StorageOS cluster maps one-to-one to a Kubernetes (or similar
orchestrator) cluster, and we expect our container to run on all worker
nodes within the cluster that will consume or present storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clusters use etcd to maintain state and manage distributed consensus between
nodes. We offer a choice between an internally managed etcd suitable for test
installations or the ability to interface with an external etcd, suitable for
production deployments. We recommend the use of external etcd when production
or production like workloads will be deployed on StorageOS.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Compression</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/compression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/compression/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS compression is handled on a per volume basis and is enabled by
default, as performance is generally increased when compression is enabled due
to fewer read/write operations taking place on the backend store (the volumes&amp;rsquo;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/volumes#blob-files&#34;&gt;blob files&lt;/a&gt;). Compression can be disabled
by setting the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/reference/labels&#34;&gt;label&lt;/a&gt; &lt;code&gt;storageos.com/nocompress=true&lt;/code&gt;
on a volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS utilises the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lz4.github.io/lz4/&#34;&gt;lz4 compression algorithm&lt;/a&gt;
when writing to the backend store and when compressing &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/replication&#34;&gt;replication
traffic&lt;/a&gt; before it is sent across the network.
Compression is granular per 4k block and data will remain
compressed/uncompressed once written to a volume. Therefore, compression can be
dynamically enabled and disabled by setting the &lt;code&gt;storageos.com/nocompress&lt;/code&gt;
label on a volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS detects whether a block can be compressed or not by creating a
heuristic that predicts the size of a compressed block. If the heuristic
indicates that the compressed block is likely to be larger than the
original block then the uncompressed block is stored. Block size increases post
compression if the compression dictionary is added to a block that cannot be
compressed. By verifying whether blocks can be compressed, disk efficiency is
increased and CPU resources are not wasted on attempts to compress
uncompressible blocks. StorageOS&amp;rsquo; patented on disk format is used to tell
whether individual blocks are compressed without overhead. As such volume
compression can be dynamically enabled/disabled even while a volume is in use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When compression and &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/encryption&#34;&gt;encryption&lt;/a&gt; are both enabled
for a volume, blocks are compressed then encrypted.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Encryption</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/encryption/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/encryption/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Encryption is enabled on a per volume basis using the
&lt;code&gt;storageos.com/encryption&lt;/code&gt; label (for more information see &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/encrypted-volumes&#34;&gt;Encrypted
Volumes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS encrypts volumes on disk using AES-256 in XTS-AES mode with 512 bit
keys as recommended by &lt;a href=&#34;https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/Legacy/SP/nistspecialpublication800-38e.pdf&#34;&gt;NIST&lt;/a&gt;, with encryption keys being derived using &lt;a href=&#34;https://eprint.iacr.org/2010/264.pdf&#34;&gt;HKDF&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keys and Initialisation vectors are generated using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://godoc.org/crypto/rand&#34;&gt;crypto/rand&lt;/a&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Usage&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Volume&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;512 bits random data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Used by XTS-AES to encrypt and decrypt disk blocks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Namespace&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;256 bits random data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Used to encrypt Volume keys&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Initialisation Vector&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;256 bits random data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Used as &amp;lsquo;salt&amp;rsquo; when encrypting volume keys with namespace keys&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The components required to derive the encryption key are stored in a Kubernetes
secret. By default these secrets are stored in the namespace that StorageOS is
installed into. As Kubernetes secrets are only base64 encoded, it is recommend
to &lt;a href=&#34;https://kubernetes.io/docs/tasks/administer-cluster/encrypt-data/&#34;&gt;encrypt secrets at
rest&lt;/a&gt;.
Alternatively a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://kubernetes.io/docs/tasks/administer-cluster/kms-provider/&#34;&gt;KMS&lt;/a&gt; such
as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vaultproject.io/&#34;&gt;HashiCorp Vault&lt;/a&gt; can be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each namespace has its own key that is created when the namespace is
initialized. The namespace keys are stored as Kubernetes secrets named
&lt;code&gt;ns-key.{Namespace Name}&lt;/code&gt;. The namespace key secrets are created in whatever
namespace StorageOS is installed into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the example below there are two &lt;code&gt;ns-key&lt;/code&gt; secrets in the &lt;code&gt;storageos&lt;/code&gt;
namespace because a StorageOS volume has been provisioned in the &lt;code&gt;default&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;mongo&lt;/code&gt; namespaces. A &lt;code&gt;ns-key&lt;/code&gt; is created for a namespace regardless of whether
an encrypted volume exists in the namespace or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;background-color:#f8f8f8;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;$ kubectl get secrets -n storageos &lt;span style=&#34;color:#000;font-weight:bold&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; grep ns-key
ns-key.default                                 Opaque                                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#0000cf;font-weight:bold&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;      4d
ns-key.mongo                                   Opaque                                &lt;span style=&#34;color:#0000cf;font-weight:bold&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;      5h
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A volume is encrypted with a volume key that is a randomly generated 512 bit
key. Rather than storing the volume key, StorageOS stores an encrypted version
of the volume key, called the volume user key, which is generated by encrypting
the volume key with a 256 bit namespace key and 256 bit initialization vector. Each
namespace has a unique key and a unique initialization vector is generated
for each volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The volume key is discarded to avoid the key that encrypts user data being
compromised. Whenever the volume needs to be decrypted the volume key is
derived by decrypting the volume user key using the namespace key and initialisation
vector that are stored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to check that the volume key has been correctly derived, a key digest
of the volume key is stored to verify the derived volume key is identical to
the original key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this means that the volume user key, initialisation vector, a digest
of the volume key and the namespace key are stored in a Kubernetes secret. See
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/encrypted-volumes&#34;&gt;Encrypted Volumes&lt;/a&gt; for best practices
regarding backing up StorageOS secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Fencing</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/fencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/fencing/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;In order to understand what Fencing is and why it is a useful feature it&amp;rsquo;s
important to understand the behaviour of StatefulSets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kubernetes does reschedule pods from some controllers when nodes become
unavailable. The default behaviour is that when a node becomes unavailable its
status becomes &amp;ldquo;Unknown&amp;rdquo; and after the pod-eviction-timeout has passed pods are
scheduled for deletion. By default, the pod-eviction-timeout is five minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StatefulSets are the de facto Kubernetes controller to use for stateful
applications. The StatefulSet controller offers guarantees around pod
uniqueness, sticky identities and the persistence of PVCs beyond the lifetime
of the pod. As such, StatefulSets have different characteristics and provide
different guarantees than Deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployments guarantee the amount of healthy replicas by reconciling the state
of the cluster with the declared desired state. Attempts to align the cluster
state with the desired state happen as fast as possible by aggressively
initializing and terminating pods. If one pod is terminating, another will be
automatically scheduled to start even if the first pod is not yet completely
terminated. Stateless applications benefit from this behaviour as one pod
executes the same work as any other in the deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StatefulSets, on the other hand, guarantee that every pod scheduled has a
unique identity, which is to say that only a single copy of the pod is running
in the cluster at any one time. Whenever scheduling decisions are made, the
StatefulSet controller ensures that only one copy of a pod is running. If a pod
is deleted, a new pod will not be scheduled until the first pod is fully
terminated. This is an important guarantee considering that FileSystems
need to be unmounted before they can be remounted in a new pod. Any PVC
defining a device requires this behaviour to ensure the consistency of the
data and thus the PVC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of the guarantee of unique pod identity, StatefulSet pods
don&amp;rsquo;t get rescheduled upon node failures. This is because Kubernetes is unable to
reason about whether the node is temporarily unavailable due to a network
partition or if the node has crashed. Therefore, the StatefulSet controller
cannot guarantee that if it reschedules an unavailable pod that the pod is not
still running. The original pod would be running on the partitioned node and
the rescheduled pod would be running on a different node, in violation of the
StatefulSet guarantee of pod uniqueness. Instead, the StatefulSet controller
slates the pod on the partitioned node for termination, but since there is
no communication between the node and the control plane, the termination cannot
be actioned by the partitioned node. The control plane will then mark the pod
status as &amp;ldquo;Unknown&amp;rdquo; while it waits for the partition to heal or for a manual
intervention by the cluster operator. The partitioned node doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any
changes to its pods as there&amp;rsquo;s no communication between the node and the
Kubernetes control plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on the rationale behind the design of StatefulSets please
see the Kubernetes design proposal for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kubernetes/community/blob/master/contributors/design-proposals/storage/pod-safety.md&#34;&gt;Pod
Safety&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;HA for StatefulSet applications can be achieved with the StorageOS Fencing
feature&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS implements a feature known as Fencing. With Fencing, pods that are
scheduled on a failed node can be terminated by StorageOS allowing the pods to
be scheduled on a different node. StorageOS can determine if a pod should be
rescheduled by leveraging StorageOS health checks that are already used to
ensure high availability of data and failover. Without Fencing, the pod will be
slated for termination but this can only be actioned when the unavailable node
rejoins the cluster or the unavailable node is deleted from the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As explained in &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/fencing#statefulset-behaviour&#34;&gt;StatefulSet
Behaviour&lt;/a&gt;, the StatefulSet
controller is conservative by design, given the constraints of various types of
persistent volumes that can be managed in Kubernetes. For certain workloads,
when StorageOS has declared a node offline it may be desirable to promote
faster pod rescheduling by allowing StorageOS to Fence pods on the unavailable
node. By enabling Fencing, StatefulSet pods have a much shorter time to recover
(TTR) than usual and no manual intervention is required for StatefulSet pods on
failed nodes to be rescheduled. Hence, &lt;em&gt;the combination of StorageOS volume
failover and StorageOS Fencing makes an application more resilient to node
failures with automatic recovery and a 30-60 second TTR.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a StorageOS pod runs on each node in the cluster that consumes or presents
storage, and these nodes communicate using a gossip protocol, StorageOS has
additional insight into whether a node cannot communicate with the master or if
the node is truly unavailable. Additionally due to the synchronous replication
of StorageOS volumes, any writes made to the volume on the partitioned node
will fail as the writes cannot be acknowledged by replica volumes. Therefore,
in a scenario where the node is unreachable StorageOS knows that the pod will
lose access to its data so it is safe for StorageOS to force the pod to be
rescheduled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about how to enable Fencing please see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/fencing&#34;&gt;Fencing
Operations&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Metrics</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/metrics/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS believes in exposing many metrics about the functioning and
performance of StorageOS processes to help users instrument applications
consuming StorageOS volumes and StorageOS itself. To this end StorageOS exposes
metrics via a Prometheus endpoint on each StorageOS pod. See our &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/reference/prometheus&#34;&gt;Prometheus
Endpoint&lt;/a&gt; reference page for specific details about
what metrics are exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS metrics are exposed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://prometheus.io/docs/instrumenting/exposition_formats/#text-based-format&#34;&gt;Prometheus text
format&lt;/a&gt;,
so collectors such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://prometheus.io&#34;&gt;Prometheus&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.influxdata.com/time-series-platform/telegraf/&#34;&gt;Telegraf&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sensu.io/&#34;&gt;Sensu&lt;/a&gt; can be used. Prometheus text format exposes data as
time series where each time series can be one of four &lt;a href=&#34;https://prometheus.io/docs/concepts/metric_types/&#34;&gt;Prometheus metric
types&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Metric Name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Example Metric&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Counter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cumulative metric that only increases. Can be reset to zero on a restart&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;storageos_volume_backend_read_bytes_total&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Gauge&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Metric that can increase or decrease&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;storageos_volume_size_bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Histogram&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cumulative metric that includes information about the distribution of samples&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;storageos_local_leader_known_nodes_sync_seconds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Summary&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Similar to a histogram but calculates quantiles over certain time windows&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;go_gc_duration_second&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time series is identified by a metric name and &lt;a href=&#34;http://opentsdb.net/overview.html&#34;&gt;key-value
labels&lt;/a&gt;. The key-value labels allow multiple
dimensions for a metric to be exposed. For example the
&lt;code&gt;storageos_volume_backend_read_bytes_total&lt;/code&gt; metric is given for each volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Prometheus to scrape metrics endpoints in Kubernetes is quite elegant as
Prometheus can be configured to scrape metrics from Kubernetes Services. This
is important because StorageOS metrics are intended to be scraped from every
StorageOS pod in the cluster and then aggregated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example of how to visualize StorageOS metrics please see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/monitoring#analysing-metrics&#34;&gt;Monitoring
StorageOS page&lt;/a&gt; for a link to a
sample Grafana dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Namespaces</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/namespaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/namespaces/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS namespaces are an identical concept to Kubernetes namespaces. They
are intended to allow a StorageOS cluster to be used by multiple teams across
multiple projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not necessary to create StorageOS namespaces manually, as StorageOS maps
Kubernetes namespaces on a one-to-one basis when PersistentVolumeClaims using
the StorageOS StorageClass are created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to Namespaces is controlled through user or group level &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/policies/&#34;&gt;policies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Nodes</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/nodes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/nodes/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;A StorageOS node is any machine (virtual or physical) that is running the
StorageOS container. Under Kubernetes orchestration a StorageOS container
runs as part of a Kubernetes pod on all Kubernetes worker node. StorageOS nodes
aggregate host storage and present this storage as StorageOS &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/pools/&#34;&gt;pools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Policies</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/policies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/policies/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS policies are a way to control user and group access to StorageOS
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/namespaces/&#34;&gt;Namespaces&lt;/a&gt;. To grant a user or group
access to a namespace, a policy needs to be created mapping the user or group
to the namespace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Users always have access to the default namespace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on how to use policies, see the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/policies/&#34;&gt;Policies operations&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Pools</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/pools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/pools/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS aggregates host storage from all nodes where the StorageOS container
runs into a storage pool. A pool is a collection of storage based on host
attributes such as class of server, storage or location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Node storage can be allocated to a specific pool using Node selectors. Pool node
selectors look for labels on host nodes and will aggregate storage from nodes
whose labels match into the specific pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pools can have feature labels applied to them such as
&lt;code&gt;storageos.com/overcommit&lt;/code&gt; which allows the pool to have its storage
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/overcommitment/&#34;&gt;overcommited&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Replication</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/replication/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/replication/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS replicates volumes across nodes for data protection and high
availability. Synchronous replication ensures strong consistency for
applications such as databases and Elasticsearch, incurring one network round
trip on writes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic model for StorageOS replication is of a master volume with distributed
replicas. Each volume can be replicated between 0 and 5 times, which are
provisioned to 0 to 5 nodes, up to the number of remaining nodes in the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this diagram, the master volume &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt; was created on node 1, and two replicas,
&lt;code&gt;D2&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;D3&lt;/code&gt; on nodes 3 and 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/images/docs/concepts/high-availability.png&#34; alt=&#34;StorageOS replication&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writes that come into &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt; (step 1) are written in parallel to &lt;code&gt;D2&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;D3&lt;/code&gt;
(step 2). When both replicas and the master acknowledge that the data has been
written (step 3), the write operation return successfully to the application
(step 4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most applications, one replica is sufficient (&lt;code&gt;storageos.com/replicas=1&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All replication traffic on the wire is compressed using the lz4 algorithm, then
streamed over tcp/ip to target port tcp/5703.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the master volume is lost, a random replica is promoted to master (&lt;code&gt;D2&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code&gt;D3&lt;/code&gt; above) and a new replica is created and synced on an available node (Node 2
or 4). This is transparent to the application and does not cause downtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a replica volume is lost and there are enough remaining nodes, a new replica
is created and synced on an available node. While a new replica is created and
being synced, the volume&amp;rsquo;s health will be marked as degraded and the failure
mode will determine whether the volume can be used during recovery:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Failure mode&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;On loss of replica&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Hard&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;If the number of replicas falls below that requested, mark the volume as unavailable. Any reads or writes will fail.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;storageos.com/failure.mode=hard&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Always On&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;As long as any copy of the volume is available, the volume will be usable.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;storageos.com/failure.mode=alwayson&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Soft&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Default mode. Specify how many failed replicas to tolerate, defaulting to 1 if there is only 1 replica, or replicas - 1 if there is more than 1 replica.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;storageos.com/failure.mode=soft storageos.com/failure.tolerance=2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While replica count and replication failure mode are controllable on a
per-volume basis, some environments may prefer to set appropriate policies to
ensure a desired level of data protection. This can be accomplished on a
per-namespace basis  using
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/rules/&#34;&gt;Rules&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Rules</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/rules/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/rules/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Rules are used for managing data policy and placement using StorageOS features
such as replication, QoS and compression. They provide a way for operators to
define default charactistics (such as number of replicas).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rules are defined using labels and selectors. When a volume is created, the
rules are evaluated to determine whether to apply the action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example business requirement might be that all production volumes are
replicated twice. This would be defined with a selector &lt;code&gt;env==prod&lt;/code&gt;, and the
action would be to add the label &lt;code&gt;storageos.com/replicas=2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rules can be created with the CLI or Web UI. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/rules/&#34;&gt;Rules&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Volumes</title>
      <link>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/volumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.storageos.com/docs/concepts/volumes/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS volumes are a logical construct which represent a writeable volume
and exhibit standard POSIX semantics. We present volumes as mounts into
containers via the Linux LIO subsystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conceptually, StorageOS volumes have a frontend presentation, which is the
side the application sees, and a backend presentation, which is the actual
on-disk format. Depending on the configuration, frontend and backend components
may be on the same or different hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volumes are formatted using the linux standard ext4 filesystem by default.
Kubernetes users may change the default filesystem type to ext2, ext3, ext4,
or xfs by setting the fsType parameter in their StorageClass (See
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/reference/filesystems#persistent-volume-filesystems&#34;&gt;Supported
Filesystems&lt;/a&gt; for
more information). Different filesystems may be supported in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS volumes are represented on disk in two parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actual volume data is written to blob files in
&lt;code&gt;/var/lib/storageos/data/dev[\d+]&lt;/code&gt;. Inside these directories, each StorageOS
block device gets two blob files of the form &lt;code&gt;vol.xxxxxx.y.blob&lt;/code&gt;, where x is
the inode number for the device, and y is an index between 0 and 1. We provide
two blob files in order to ensure that certain operations which require locking
do not impede in-flight writes to the volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In systems which have multiple &lt;code&gt;/var/lib/storageos/data/dev[\d+]&lt;/code&gt; directories,
we place two blob files per block device. This allows us to load-balance writes
across multiple devices. In cases where dev directories are added after a
period of run time, later directories are favoured for writes until the data is
distributed evenly across the blob files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metadata is kept in directories named &lt;code&gt;/var/lib/storageos/data/db[\d+]&lt;/code&gt;. We
maintain an index of all blocks written to the blob file inside the metadata
store, including checksums. These checksums allow us to detect bitrot, and
return errors on reads, rather than serve bad data. In future versions we may
implement recovery from replicas for volumes with one or more replicas defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StorageOS metadata requires approximately 2.7GB of storage per 1TB of allocated
blocks in the associated volume. This size is consistent irrespective of data
compression defined on the volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure deterministic performance, individual StorageOS volumes must fit on a single
node. In situations where &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/operations/overcommitment/&#34;&gt;overcommit&lt;/a&gt; is applied, a scaling factor is applied when determining whether to place a
volume on a node.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present various metrics regarding StorageOS volumes, including used capacity
and throughput, via our &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.storageos.com/docs/reference/prometheus/&#34;&gt;Prometheus Endpoint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
